<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<unit xmlns="http://www.sdml.info/srcML/src" xmlns:cpp="http://www.sdml.info/srcML/cpp" language="C" filename="projects/cpython-2.6.1/source/Mac/Modules/cg/CFMLateImport.h"><comment type="block">/*
	File:		CFMLateImport.h

	Contains:	Interface to CFM late import library.

	Written by:	Quinn

	Copyright:	Copyright © 1999 by Apple Computer, Inc., all rights reserved.

				You may incorporate this Apple sample source code into your program(s) without
				restriction. This Apple sample source code has been provided "AS IS" and the
				responsibility for its operation is yours. You are not permitted to redistribute
				this Apple sample source code as "Apple sample source code" after having made
				changes. If you're going to re-distribute the source, we require that you make
				it clear in the source that the code was descended from Apple sample source
				code, but that you've made changes.

	Change History (most recent first):

         &lt;6&gt;     21/9/01    Quinn   Changes for CWPro7 Mach-O build.
         &lt;5&gt;     19/9/01    Quinn   Change comments to reflect the fact that an unpacked data
                                    section is no longer required.
         &lt;4&gt;     19/9/01    Quinn   Simplified API and implementation after a suggestion by Eric
                                    Grant. You no longer have to CFM export a dummy function; you
                                    can just pass in the address of your fragment's init routine.
         &lt;3&gt;    16/11/00    Quinn   Allow symbol finding via a callback and use that to implement
                                    CFBundle support.
         &lt;2&gt;    18/10/99    Quinn   Renamed CFMLateImport to CFMLateImportLibrary to allow for
                                    possible future API expansion.
         &lt;1&gt;     15/6/99    Quinn   First checked in.
*/</comment>

<cpp:pragma>#<cpp:directive>pragma</cpp:directive> once</cpp:pragma>

<comment type="line">/////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////</comment>

<comment type="line">// MoreIsBetter Setup</comment>

<comment type="line">//#include "MoreSetup.h"</comment>

<comment type="line">// Mac OS Interfaces</comment>

<cpp:if>#<cpp:directive>if</cpp:directive> <expr>! <name>MORE_FRAMEWORK_INCLUDES</name></expr></cpp:if>
	<cpp:include>#<cpp:directive>include</cpp:directive> <cpp:file>&lt;MacTypes.h&gt;</cpp:file></cpp:include>
	<cpp:include>#<cpp:directive>include</cpp:directive> <cpp:file>&lt;CodeFragments.h&gt;</cpp:file></cpp:include>
	<cpp:include>#<cpp:directive>include</cpp:directive> <cpp:file>&lt;Devices.h&gt;</cpp:file></cpp:include>
	<cpp:include>#<cpp:directive>include</cpp:directive> <cpp:file>&lt;CFBundle.h&gt;</cpp:file></cpp:include>
<cpp:endif>#<cpp:directive>endif</cpp:directive></cpp:endif>

<comment type="line">/////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////</comment>

<cpp:ifdef>#<cpp:directive>ifdef</cpp:directive> <name>__cplusplus</name></cpp:ifdef>
<extern>extern "C" <block>{
<cpp:endif>#<cpp:directive>endif</cpp:directive></cpp:endif>

<comment type="block">/*	FAQ
	---
	
	Q:	What does this library do?
	A:	It allows you to resolve a weak linked library at runtime,
	   	by supply a CFM connection to the library that should substitute
	   	for the weak linked one.
	
	Q:	Does the substituted library have to have the same name as the
		weak linked library.
	A:	No.
	
	Q:	What's this useful for?
	A:	The most obvious example of where this is useful is when
		you rely on shared libraries that the user might delete
		or move.  To can find the shared library (possibly even
		using CatSearch), call GetDiskFragment to open a connection
		to it, late import it using this library, and then the
		rest of your code can continue to use the shared library
		as if nothing had happened.  No more defining thousands
		of stub routines which call through routine pointers.
		
		There are, however, numerous less obvious uses.  You can
		use this code to make a 'self repairing' application.  If
		the user removes your shared library from the Extensions
		folder, the startup code for your application can offer
		tor re-install it.  If the user agrees, you can then
		re-install your shared library, late import it, and then
		continue running your application if nothing happened.
		
		You can even use this code to free yourself from the
		Extensions folder entirely.  Say you have a suite of
		applications that currently installs a dozen shared 
		libraries in the Extensions folder.  You can move those
		libraries to another folder entirely and each application's
		startup code can track down the library (using an alias
		in the Preferences file) and late import it.
		
		An even cooler use is to provide easy abstraction layers.
		Say you have a network code for both the MacTCP
		API and the Open Transport API.  Typically, you would be
		force to do this by having an abstraction layer where every
		routine contains a switch between MacTCP and OT.  Your
		OpenSocket routine might look like:

			static int OpenSocket(void)
			{
			    if (gOTAvailable) {
			        return OpenSocketOT();
			    } else {
			        return OpenSocketMacTCP();
			    }
			}
		
		With this code, you can avoid that entirely.  Simply
		weak link to a shared library that you know is never
		going to be implemented ("crea;MySocketsDummy") and then, 
		at runtime, decide whether the system has MacTCP or OT
		and late import the relevant real implementation
		("crea;MySocketsMacTCP" or "crea;MySocketsOT").
		One benefit of this approach is that only the MacTCP or
		the OT code is resident in memory on any given system.
*/</comment>

<typedef>typedef <function_decl><type><name>pascal</name> <name>OSStatus</name></type> (*<name>CFMLateImportLookupProc</name>)<parameter_list>(<param><decl><type><name>ConstStr255Param</name></type> <name>symName</name></decl></param>, <param><decl><type><name>CFragSymbolClass</name></type> <name>symClass</name></decl></param>,
													<param><decl><type><name>void</name> **</type><name>symAddr</name></decl></param>, <param><decl><type><name>void</name> *</type><name>refCon</name></decl></param>)</parameter_list>;</function_decl></typedef>
	<comment type="line">// CFMLateImportLookupProc defines a callback for CFMLateImportCore.</comment>
	<comment type="line">// The routine is expected to look up the address of the symbol named </comment>
	<comment type="line">// symName and return it in *symAddr.  The symbol should be of class </comment>
	<comment type="line">// symClass, although the callback decides whether a class mismatch is </comment>
	<comment type="line">// an error.  refCon is an application defined value that was originally </comment>
	<comment type="line">// passed in to CFMLateImportCore.</comment>
	<comment type="line">//</comment>
	<comment type="line">// If this routine returns an error, a symbol address of 0 is assumed. </comment>
	<comment type="line">// If the symbol is marked as a weak import, the CFMLateImportCore will </comment>
	<comment type="line">// continue, otherwise the CFMLateImportCore routine will fail with the </comment>
	<comment type="line">// error.</comment>
	
<function_decl><type><specifier>extern</specifier> <name>pascal</name> <name>OSStatus</name></type> <name>CFMLateImportCore</name><parameter_list>(<param><decl><type><specifier>const</specifier> <name>CFragSystem7DiskFlatLocator</name> *</type><name>fragToFixLocator</name></decl></param>,
										<param><decl><type><name>CFragConnectionID</name></type> <name>fragToFixConnID</name></decl></param>,
										<param><decl><type><name>CFragInitFunction</name></type> <name>fragToFixInitRoutine</name></decl></param>,
										<param><decl><type><name>ConstStr255Param</name></type> <name>weakLinkedLibraryName</name></decl></param>,
										<param><decl><type><name>CFMLateImportLookupProc</name></type> <name>lookup</name></decl></param>,
										<param><decl><type><name>void</name> *</type><name>refCon</name></decl></param>)</parameter_list>;</function_decl>
	<comment type="line">// This routine will link you, at runtime, to some library </comment>
	<comment type="line">// that you were weak linked to and wasn't present when your</comment>
	<comment type="line">// fragment was prepared.  As well as the obvious functionality</comment>
	<comment type="line">// of being able to resolve weak links after prepare time,</comment>
	<comment type="line">// this functionality can be put to a number of less obvious uses,</comment>
	<comment type="line">// some of which are discussed at the top of this header file.</comment>
	<comment type="line">//</comment>
	<comment type="line">// To call this routine, you need a number of pieces of information:</comment>
	<comment type="line">//</comment>
	<comment type="line">// 1. fragToFixLocator, fragToFixConnID:  The location of your own</comment>
	<comment type="line">//    code fragment on disk and the CFM connection ID to your own</comment>
	<comment type="line">//    code fragment.  Typically you get this information from your </comment>
	<comment type="line">//    fragment's CFM init routine.  You must ensure that</comment>
	<comment type="line">//    fragToFixLocator-&gt;fileSpec points to an FSSpec of the</comment>
	<comment type="line">//    file which holds your code fragment.</comment>
	<comment type="line">//</comment>
	<comment type="line">//    IMPORTANT:</comment>
	<comment type="line">//    The fact that you pass in a CFragSystem7DiskFlatLocator as the</comment>
	<comment type="line">//    fragToFixLocator implies that the fragment to be fixed up must</comment>
	<comment type="line">//    be in the data fork of a file.  The code could be modified</comment>
	<comment type="line">//    to remove this requirement, but on disk code fragments are the most</comment>
	<comment type="line">//    common case.</comment>
	<comment type="line">//</comment>
	<comment type="line">//    IMPORTANT:</comment>
	<comment type="line">//    The fragment to fix may have a packed data section.  Packing the </comment>
	<comment type="line">//    data section will reduce the size of your fragment on disk, but it </comment>
	<comment type="line">//    will significantly increase the memory needed by this routine </comment>
	<comment type="line">//    (it increases memory usage by the sum of the sizes of the packed </comment>
	<comment type="line">//    and unpacked data section).  See below for instructions on how to </comment>
	<comment type="line">//    create an unpacked data section.</comment>
	<comment type="line">//</comment>
	<comment type="line">// 2. fragToFixInitRoutine:  A pointer to your own code fragment's</comment>
	<comment type="line">//    fragment initialiser routine.  You necessarily have one of these </comment>
	<comment type="line">//    because you need it to get values for the fragToFixLocator and </comment>
	<comment type="line">//    fragToFixConnID parameters.  Just pass its address in as a parameter </comment>
	<comment type="line">//    as well. </comment>
	<comment type="line">//</comment>
	<comment type="line">// 3. weakLinkedLibraryName:  The name of the weak linked library which</comment>
	<comment type="line">//    failed to link.  You must have weak linked to this library.</comment>
	<comment type="line">//    It is oxymoric for you to pass a strong linked library here,</comment>
	<comment type="line">//    because your code would not have prepared if a strong linked</comment>
	<comment type="line">//    library failed to prepare, and so you couldn't supply a valid</comment>
	<comment type="line">///   fragToFix.</comment>
	<comment type="line">//</comment>
	<comment type="line">// 4. lookup, refCon:  A pointer to a callback function that the </comment>
	<comment type="line">//	  routine calls to look up the address of a symbol, and a refCon </comment>
	<comment type="line">//    for that callback routine.</comment>
	<comment type="line">//</comment>
	<comment type="line">// Note:</comment>
	<comment type="line">// The fragToFixLocator and fragToFixInitRoutine parameters</comment>
	<comment type="line">// are artifacts of the way in which this functionality is implemented.</comment>
	<comment type="line">// In an ideal world, where CFM exported decent introspection APIs</comment>
	<comment type="line">// to third party developers, these parameters would not be necessary.</comment>
	<comment type="line">// If you're using this code inside Apple, you probably should investigate</comment>
	<comment type="line">// using the CFM private APIs for getting at the information these</comment>
	<comment type="line">// parameters are needed for.  See the comments inside the implementation</comment>
	<comment type="line">// for more details.</comment>
	<comment type="line">//</comment>
	<comment type="line">// Note:</comment>
	<comment type="line">// The extra memory taken when you use a packed data section is also an </comment>
	<comment type="line">// artifact of my workaround for the lack of CFM introspection APIs.  In </comment>
	<comment type="line">// my opinion it's better to use an unpacked data section and consume more </comment>
	<comment type="line">// space on disk while saving memory.  In CodeWarrior you can switch to an </comment>
	<comment type="line">// unpacked data section by checking the "Expand Uninitialized Data" </comment>
	<comment type="line">// checkbox in the "PPC PEF" settings panel.  In MPW, specified the</comment>
	<comment type="line">// "-packdata off" option to PPCLink.</comment>
	<comment type="line">//</comment>
	<comment type="line">// When the routine returns, any symbols that you imported from the</comment>
	<comment type="line">// library named weakLinkedLibraryName will be resolved to the address</comment>
	<comment type="line">// of the symbol provided by the "lookup" callback routine.</comment>
	<comment type="line">//</comment>
	<comment type="line">// It is possible for an unresolved import to remain unresolved after</comment>
	<comment type="line">// this routine returns.  If the symbol import is marked as weak (as</comment>
	<comment type="line">// opposed to the library, which *must* be marked as weak) and the symbol</comment>
	<comment type="line">// is not found by the "lookup" callback, the routine will simple skip </comment>
	<comment type="line">// that symbol.  If the symbol isn't marked as weak, the routine will fail </comment>
	<comment type="line">// in that case.</comment>
	<comment type="line">//</comment>
	<comment type="line">// Most of the possible error results are co-opted CFM errors.  These</comment>
	<comment type="line">// include:</comment>
	<comment type="line">//</comment>
	<comment type="line">// cfragFragmentFormatErr  -- The fragment to fix is is an unknown format.</comment>
	<comment type="line">// cfragNoSectionErr       -- Could not find the loader section in the fragment to fix.</comment>
	<comment type="line">// cfragNoLibraryErr       -- The fragment to fix is not weak linked to weakLinkedLibraryName.</comment>
	<comment type="line">// cfragFragmentUsageErr   -- The fragment to fix doesn't have a data section.</comment>
	<comment type="line">//                         -- The fragment to fix is strong linked to weakLinkedLibraryName.</comment>
	<comment type="line">//                         -- The fragment doesn't have an init routine.</comment>
	<comment type="line">// cfragFragmentCorruptErr -- Encountered an undefined relocation opcode.</comment>
	<comment type="line">// unimpErr                -- Encountered an unimplement relocation opcode.  The</comment>
	<comment type="line">//                            relocation engine only implements a subset of the CFM</comment>
	<comment type="line">//                            relocation opcodes, the subset most commonly used by</comment>
	<comment type="line">//                            MPW and CodeWarrior PEF containers.  If you encounter</comment>
	<comment type="line">//                            this error, you'll probably have to add the weird</comment>
	<comment type="line">//                            relocation opcode to the engine, which shouldn't be</comment>
	<comment type="line">//                            be too hard.</comment>
	<comment type="line">// memFullErr			   -- It's likely that this error is triggered by the memory </comment>
	<comment type="line">//                            needed to unpack your data section.  Either make your </comment>
	<comment type="line">//                            data section smaller, or unpack it (see above).</comment>
	<comment type="line">// errors returned by FindSymbol</comment>
	<comment type="line">// errors returned by Memory Manager</comment>
	<comment type="line">//</comment>
	<comment type="line">// The routine needs enough memory to hold the loader section of the fragment</comment>
	<comment type="line">// to fix in memory.  It allocates that memory using NewPtr and dispsoses of </comment>
	<comment type="line">// it before it returns.  You may want to change the memory allocator, which</comment>
	<comment type="line">// is very simple.</comment>

<function_decl><type><specifier>extern</specifier> <name>pascal</name> <name>OSStatus</name></type> <name>CFMLateImportLibrary</name><parameter_list>(<param><decl><type><specifier>const</specifier> <name>CFragSystem7DiskFlatLocator</name> *</type><name>fragToFixLocator</name></decl></param>,
										<param><decl><type><name>CFragConnectionID</name></type> <name>fragToFixConnID</name></decl></param>,
										<param><decl><type><name>CFragInitFunction</name></type> <name>fragToFixInitRoutine</name></decl></param>,
										<param><decl><type><name>ConstStr255Param</name></type> <name>weakLinkedLibraryName</name></decl></param>,
										<param><decl><type><name>CFragConnectionID</name></type> <name>connIDToImport</name></decl></param>)</parameter_list>;</function_decl>
	<comment type="line">// A wrapper around CFMLateImportCore that looks up symbols by calling </comment>
	<comment type="line">// FindSymbol on a connection to a CFM library (connIDToImport).</comment>
	<comment type="line">// You can get this connection ID through any standard CFM API, for example</comment>
	<comment type="line">// GetSharedLibrary, GetDiskFragment, or GetMemFragment.</comment>
	<comment type="line">//</comment>
	<comment type="line">// IMPORTANT:</comment>
	<comment type="line">// The fragment name for connIDToImport *does not* have to match</comment>
	<comment type="line">// weakLinkedLibraryName.  This is part of the power of this library.</comment>

<function_decl><type><specifier>extern</specifier> <name>pascal</name> <name>OSStatus</name></type> <name>CFMLateImportBundle</name><parameter_list>(<param><decl><type><specifier>const</specifier> <name>CFragSystem7DiskFlatLocator</name> *</type><name>fragToFixLocator</name></decl></param>,
										<param><decl><type><name>CFragConnectionID</name></type> <name>fragToFixConnID</name></decl></param>,
										<param><decl><type><name>CFragInitFunction</name></type> <name>fragToFixInitRoutine</name></decl></param>,
										<param><decl><type><name>ConstStr255Param</name></type> <name>weakLinkedLibraryName</name></decl></param>,
										<param><decl><type><name>CFBundleRef</name></type> <name>bundleToImport</name></decl></param>)</parameter_list>;</function_decl>
	<comment type="line">// A wrapper around CFMLateImportCore that looks up symbols by calling </comment>
	<comment type="line">// CFBundleGetFunctionPointerForName on a reference to a Core Foundation </comment>
	<comment type="line">// bundle (bundleToImport).  You can get this reference through any </comment>
	<comment type="line">// Core Foundation bundle API, for example CFBundleCreate.</comment>

<cpp:ifdef>#<cpp:directive>ifdef</cpp:directive> <name>__cplusplus</name></cpp:ifdef>
}</block></extern>
<cpp:endif>#<cpp:directive>endif</cpp:directive></cpp:endif>
</unit>
